It's just the movement of the endoderm.
We see it in its entirety, as we saw in the short film,
but also transversely from a sac to a tube ultimately.
Why? Because not only does the amniotic cavity make this movement,
but laterally it also makes this movement.
So it completely encompasses the embryo,
as you gradually understand the integration of this digestive tube from the outside to
the inside
organized by the amniotic cavity but mainly directed by the
primitive aortic arch.
You see, if we focus solely on the vascular plan, this drawing should be
much
larger, and this one even bigger, and this one even larger, and this one
again.
Primitive endocardium
tightens simultaneously
as I have the closure of my neural tube
and the meeting of the two
here will create a space
within the lumen
of my endoderm
yolk sac
primordial to form
what we call the
pharyngeal gut
and this occurs along the
midline, the meeting
of these two will create
what is called the pharyngeal intestine, and laterally, the coelom will
appear.
So it's the differential growth of epithelial tissue relative to connective tissue
that causes my two aortas to come closer together along the central axis
which will delineate the longitudinal axis and create the pharyngeal gut.
There, we have already analyzed an initial image which was the internal image,
with the formation of the vital system.
One to form what we call the pharyngeal intestine, the upper intestine, the
upper part,
the intestine here, from the mouth to the mid-section. We saw how
it happens. This will
involve the face. Now, we will study from the periphery to the center. So
initially,
when looking at an embryo, I am well before the flexion, so
I am around the 15th day,
the end of the second week.
Let's say, I can divide the embryo into three parts,
upper third, middle third, lower third.
And I observe that at this stage, the head of the future embryo is huge
compared to a small trunk.
The part here corresponds already to the cephalic part,
and this one to the trunk.
And then, it will elongate significantly in this region.
This means that half of the embryo will initially be found
on my skull base, on the plane of the symphysis.
with the notochordal field, relative to the primitive line.
Primitive line, notochordal axis.
What causes the flexion? It's the vascular system.
The fold.
Now, taking a simple diagram, I take a tube.
It will bend, this tube.
I have one area that densifies and one area that stretches.
So, that will form this.
If I take another shape, it will look like this.
It will form folds through densification.
And I will make a section of the embryo like this.
Inside here.
Here, I have endodermic tissue, outside the ectodermic tissue,
and between the two here, I have what we call mesodermic tissue,
future cartilage if you will.
It's the same section that is here, add it here, section of the embryo,
and I see here, more precisely, different
brachial arches that contain specific information.
but organized in space relative to the entirety of
the embryo.
And what is the information that is found?
It's that each branchial arch is organized on a nearly
facial plane,
always towards the same level, and towards which
?
Towards what we call the base of the skull.
It's like rings, people doing the
hula hoop.
I take the ring and I take a ring here.
Imagine, I have Urmian rings and
below, I have four rings that will form the
mandibular arches.
And the strength of these arches, all, will orient towards what?
towards my skull base. So also my skull, my
neuromuscular system, on a mesodermic plane of organization
by what we call the dural sheaths, and on another
plane by the sheaths, let’s say facial,
all orient towards the base of the skull. In other words, I cannot
treat a skull base except through its periphery,
the mandibular branch, the dural sheath, actually come
together towards the base of the
skull.
And it is there where I must find integrity, either I am deviated or anything,
you see.
So treating a face, treating a skull, is to return it
to this primitive function,
like an energetic field, like this, like a current.
that organizes itself towards that space.
Both here
and hyoid
and laryngeal
upper or lower.
Also
in the anterior dural sheath
and posterior.
But each field
contains specific information
that can be said
to symbolically
have four major branchial arches.
There are a few more, but we see
There are four truly functional ones, the mandibular arch, the
hyoid arch, the
upper laryngeal arch, and the lower laryngeal arch
and there’s another that will disappear.
Each arch, both on an ectodermic plane or on a mesodermic plane or on an endodermic plane, has information.
The mandibular arch contains information with the mandibular cartilage,
but we see that from this same arch will appear structures of the inner ear.
This means that destabilization of the jaw will automatically reflect
on the information of the internal organization of the ear,
essentially the malleus.
and the incus, while the stapes will be part of the styloid cartilage,
which contains
the styloid process, up to the upper part of the thyroid cartilage.
When I take this arch, I actually have a structural tone in hand.
I have both the mandible, I have both the inner ear,
malleus, incus,
I have both the system towards my skull base and
I actually have to bring them into the full-structured
embryonic matrix, it's my skull base, it's here so
it contains not only information
cartilaginous muscular vascular neurological; I find myself with a
picture where, for example, the
branch of the pharyngeal arch in terms of the artery
I will have the terminal branch of the maxillary artery,
and I will find myself with cartilaginous derivatives that come from the neural crest,
because we will add the neural crest in this story,
and I will see the maxillary cartilage like the lesser sphenoid, the incus,
the mandibular cartilage, the malleus,
all the derivatives of the ossification of the dermal mesenchyme from the arch,
like the maxilla, the zygomatic bone, the squamous part,
and the temporal bone and the mandible,
from the same arch
with the same muscle
so I have creative forces
that at first
is just a simple movement
between the ectoderm
the mesoderm and the endoderm
but all organized on its
full embryonic structure
when I take a point of support
at this level here
I simply return its functional points
its point of support, its full structure
the tissue is what it should
do. If someone comes and receives a good hit in the face, they are deviated.
Or if there is an accident, or if there is a dental trauma, or if there is a craniosacral dysfunction,
it can disturb the entire system. This is neural crest. It's a primitive invasion
in this phase of flexion of the embryo. I have the neural tube closing and
I have
these lips of the neural tube that are here, you see, on the side. And from there, there will be
At that level, what we call rhombomery, which will divide into different zones.
So the rhombomere will give 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
A phase of migration like this.
Is happening here, this is the impulse of my neural crest.
At the moment I have this phase of flexion, I have everything organizing towards
my spheno-basilar symphysis.
It's all this phase, you see.
of integration like this, of this proliferation.
We call it the outpouring of the neural crest.
And this means that the quality of the tissue that is here, up to there, with the platysma,
is not the same as that which is here or there.
However, you find this same neural quality in
your digestive tube.
The dermis, the muscles, the bone, all that,
is neural crest.
But this happens synchronously with the movement of flexion and
orientation.
The neural crest does this, you see, we see, and all the lines of force
do this towards my skull base.
The neural crest starts from the posterior part here, and here in this movement of flexion,
it's not just that it does this, it's that it already builds like this, you see, around the system.
You have to imagine that this embryo grows.
not only in the movement of flexion but also elongates.
And in this elongation process, I have the whole process of cerebralization,
the formation of my prosencephalic system and the process of telencephalization.
And with the process of intracranial-ventricular elimination
that will follow this movement on the level of the development of my telencephalon,
but also outside of Urmian.
my dural sheaths, that will form my ventricles and will organize the whole of my
embryo.
This developmental movement occurs in a biodynamic process.
We see here an embryo at the third week that has just begun its flexion
and we see here that the embryo is already open.
This is the brain in formation and here we see the closure of
what is called the anterior neuropore.
We see here the mandibular arch.
the pharyngeal membrane, and we see the cardiac zone.
Then it advances, we already see that the process of cerebralization really comes towards
the front,
and we already see an organization, still the cardiac zone,
and we can already see the mouth, future mouth, which will develop here.
And in fact, we can say that the face, the facial structure, is the expression of the
establishment of the heart.
The heart develops between the chin, the neural tube,
and the liver or diaphragm.
It's a compression between the heart and the
brain that will create the face.
That's why we will find a child's face,
or an adult's, with a typology of type mental, cerebral,
cardiac or hepatic.
My face must be a balance between my brain, my heart,
and my liver. We find again
two types, typology
ectodermic, mesodermic or endodermic
where we find what we call
vata, pitta and kapha
in Ayurvedic medicine for example.
Now we will go from the periphery
to the inside. So what do I see here? At one point
I have the rupture of the disintegration
of the buccopharyngeal membrane.
In front, the first hymen
here, will rupture.
This first mandibular arch
is an arch that contains the maxilla and the mandible. Initially, they will function
in
a unit. All this is a mandibular arch then it will organize
by my mouth actually
which will give the information. So it's my digestive system and the organization
of the anterior
compression of my pharyngeal membrane that makes my mouth develop
in one direction
horizontally. It's like this because it's the meeting.
between my heart and my brain that creates this space and the compression will
integrate my mesodermic tissue which contains the vascular information; if it
is
compressed, I will have no vascular information and I have
lines that will create what we call a corrosion field on a
metabolic level. So at this very moment I see the appearance of what we call a
nasal pit here and the oral cavity now if I put you these
images, we could say ah yes, but it has
dug; in fact, no it hasn't dug, it is becoming
a point of support here regarding the system because I have a frenum and
this frenum comes from a system
here, from a relationship with my nasal placode which is a relationship
just an acrine with specific metabolic information with what we call the olfactory placode.
It's the meeting between the deep ectoderm
and the surface ectoderm, which creates a point of attachment, but the system continues.
And it's from there that I will have this coiling, and this is how I have the part
of the nose or the upper part that begins to develop, with this fixed point here.
So my ethmoid becomes, relative to my system, another point of support for
my flexion.
Relative to my olfactory placode. It's a view from below, the palate still
open, with the palatine cleft.
Initially, this line had opened. It's a view as you just saw, but at a
premature stage, before the closure of this palate. Now here, it's just a schematic section
of my
spheno-basilar symphysis. And more specifically, it’s a section where I will integrate
in this diagram
the development of the brain.
in relation to the process of telencephalization,
what we call the brain ascent process,
relative to the process of visceral descent.
This means that my face, initially, is a field of compression between my heart and my brain,
and then through the general growth of my embryo, it will open.
And so I have not only a movement that will happen longitudinally,
like this, but also like...
this diagram here represents my sphenoid with
the part here in front called the two
and you imagine now
here that's the part here called the cristagalli; we will study that with
the process of my brain. You remember it was like this, and then I have the
closure of the two lobes of the prosencephalon which will
form the telencephalon; that will
form what we call the
of the brain, by the
growth, pulls upwards.
Then my
pterygoid processes which are lateral, here,
I have something that pulls down,
and I have something that pulls up. So the face
at first, is compression,
now, a second force
that has to be imagined, is a global elongation
of my embryo longitudinally.
And additionally,
a traction backwards that will form my falx cerebri. So
you imagine my little
pterygoids that are there, it does this, and through the traction of
the falx cerebri and the movement
of telencephalization, it does this. And
we see here that it will orient the
development
of my palatine process like this
which will form the palate
that will meet at the midline here
you see, like this
you see
to form the axis that is here
we find it here
with the ascending force of my brain
and then I have this huge pull backwards
in this movement
and I have this visceral descent downwards
sustained by the heart
but at the same moment here
I have the tissue in this movement
that will make folds
like this in the tissue
and what will that form?
it will form the rib system
you understand all my rib system will form like this, so it’s both a
synchronous development between my digestive system and my heart that
pulls downward
my cerebral system that pulls upward, the midline coming closer
of my palates and
why I have a rather ogival palate, because at the moment I have the
pull, I see that my tube here,
it does this. It is drawn upwards. And
we see
that’s why you have a palate that is ogival. At first, it was rather
flat
and by the movement of the ascensus of your brain and
the visceral traction,
It orients, and if you now look at the palate, you see something
ogival, an ogive like this, with a line along the midline.
The depth of the tongue, a long tongue, relates to extensive cephalization.
And here we see the approaching of my midline,
here, that forms along the long axis
of the embryo, which is the result of this developmental dynamic. It
comes closer, and we see
well here the palatine cleft for example, you see why it continues like this, a beak
of
lips that is a palatine cleft that is not closed on an osteopathic level; people must be operated, it's very difficult to close inside, but what do we do is it's a genetic process, we give back the longitudinal axis
of the embryo, we re-balance the brain,
we re-balance the peritoneum,
we re-balance the mediastinum.
At the same time,
I have the whole face developing,
here, I have the whole interior,
and here we see the cones forming.
Now, look,
this is the whole integration
of this movement,
that we just saw, in the form of a short film,
we will see the face,
where not only do you have
the information, remember, of my neural crest,
the longitudinal development of the embryo, the development of
the internal part, the arches
everything happens in this small drawing and you will find where the
support point
the point of meeting of the force, the support point of the face, we will
see here and we will
see this force, you see, that comes here with a support point that is here that we
call the Cristagalli, the Galen cross, there
where John the Baptist brings the consciousness
of the Christic light, that is to say, the light, to find your way
spiritual in the zone
Judeo-Christian.
But it is an important concentration of energy that is here.
The importance is still to realize that there is a large part of this
zone here that is of ectodermic origin.
with the lines of force that will be found.
But if we go even further, understanding the process of ascensus and descensus.
If we go even further, understanding that this is a neural tube that
grows,
and this is a heart that descends.
So it's a tearing between the heart that descends and
the brain that rises.
You can see clearly here the approach of my brain on this cristagalli which comes from the bone.
here, and the approach in the midline of my palatine process, the
line of force
that pulls upwards, the line of force that pulls downwards, the placodes, the nose and
the mouth that are drawn in these spaces.
The importance of my neural crest, we saw that it develops at the time of my neural tube
being formed, which will form what we call the mesectoderm, all the skeleton
of the face, the teeth, the bone, the cranial skeleton, the dermis of the face and of the neck.
The ciliary muscles and the cornea come from this information.
This means that the face, the teeth, derive from neural crests.
This means that treating the face or the teeth implies rebalancing them
with the originating rhombomere.
The mandibular arch, here, which is very important, has an origin from both
what we call the posterior mesencephalon and the rhombencephalon 1.
And two, you see, it has all this information here at the
posterior part to be rebalanced.
Every time I have a curvature that will occur, I will have a field of
constraints that will form with fields, you see, that will modify here, with polarities
that will change, with specific resorptions.
This means that axial constraints causing the curvature of a bone determine the appearance of charges
electric.
positive on the convex side and vice versa.
And calcium ions, attracted by
negative charges, accumulate in
the concavity.
And it’s the opposite on the convex side.
So you see the lines of force
that are organized.
Look at the presence here of these lines of force,
the concentrations that will
occur in this area.
Each tooth receives
a specific information, you see,
with all the integration. So the occlusal forces,
the pressures from the lingual mass and the resulting piezoelectric effects determine
the formation of these struts.
So when I take a face, I must be aware of these electrical lines,
not only on a specific plane here, you see.
When I take, I touch consciously and can delve deep.
We still see all the lines of force that will be found just in the palate.
viscera to the skull, membrane origin, cartilaginous origin.
Two types of different condensation.
Two types, one in compression, one in stretching.
We have a membranous part and a cartilaginous part.
What is important is to understand the orientation and the support points clearly.
And to superimpose all these diagrams.
And what interests me is that you...
have the idea of a movement because it is a combination
of both cephalization, cardialization,
and hepatization, and a specific orientation
with respect to this development, with specific points and fullcrum.